[Music]
hi and welcome to this episode of watch
new in my name is ESP new Christopherson
and in this episode I will discuss the
enhancements that we have made to
interfaces in this
release it is more than four years since
we first released interfaces in Al and
although it was integrated with voms
from for extensibility from the
beginning we have discovered some
limitations with that over time and with
a couple of new features we are going to
address this in this release to show how
those new features can actually help you
build better
extensibility I have created a small
sample app that I'm going to use in this
episode it is a shipping cost calculator
it allows you to enter a distance and a
weight and it will then calculate
shipping costs and it is built as a
provider model so it allows all third
parties to create their own extensions
that plugs into the model in the from
coding the own app and those will be
discovered lately and are then available
to the
calculator it is a fairly simple UI on
the top there's place to input data
distance weight and at the bottom the
different costs are shown in the
list as I mentioned it is a typical
provider model so the calculator app
defines an interface for providers to
calculate cost based on input and
there's an enome that allows the
shipping provider vendors to add
themselves into this calculator now
let's move from the slides into the
actual code
the sample app consists of three small
apps there's the shipping cost
calculator which is the orchestrator the
one that defines the interface and
actually does the calculation and con
contains the UI and then there are two
other apps that standard shipping and
express shipping they are meant to
illustrate how different vendors can add
their own calculations into the
calculator let's start with the
interface and I will just get rid of
this over there the interface is simple
it's called I shipping provider there's
a method that just Returns the provider
name it can be my own shipping or
whatever it's just a string and then
there's the method which is actually the
important part that calculate shipping
cost it calculates the cost given a
distance and a weight and returns true
if it actually calculates something
and if it returns true it will also have
populated the cost record next up is the
enum it's probably even simpler it's
just a definition of an extensible enum
called shipping vendor and it implements
the shipping provider and as you
probably know that means that all
extensions that actually adds a value
must also Define a code unit that
implements the shipping provider this is
how we built extensibility into enums
four years ago
then there's the shipping cost
orchestrator it is a code unit it
essentially Loops over all the enum
values defined by extensions to the
shipping window this is what is going on
here down there and the for each
statement for each shipping provider in
the shipping vendor it extracts the
provider which is the
interface and for all those interfaces
it cost calculate shipping cost and adds
that to the Sal Breakout set and this
code unit is called from the UI it's the
page on every changed value in the input
Fields it will call this to
calculate um costs implementing a
shipping provider is now easy for a
vendor all they need to do is to create
an enum
extension with their own name and a
value and give it a caption in this case
it's Grand Pass shipping and it defines
that I a shipping provider is
implemented by the standard shipping
provider code unit standard shipping
provider code unit in this case is also
fairly simple it has to provide the
methods defined by the interface in this
case it's the get provider name in this
case Grand Pass shipping and then it
calculates a shipping cost based on
distance and weight and this I mean this
case distance is multiplied by 0.5 and
weight is multiplied by 0.1
and and the delivery time is 5
days and it also has a description which
shows up in the UI which is reliable and
Cheap
shipping sounds good the diagram here
shows how this is the architecture
behind this there's the code unit knows
about the shipping vendor and the
shipping provider interface three top
level boxes are what is contained into
the calculator itself doesn't provide
any providers itself it relies on other
third parties to deliver their own
calculations and in this case I have
added
the uh standard shipping vendor and the
standard shipping provider at the bottom
showing how an external party can
actually add into the
calculation this is how we envisioned
this a couple of years
ago but if we
take a look at this it's not without
challenges because nothing is static
this is software at some point someone
wants to actually use Dimensions as
input or maybe at some point in the
future we want to ship to I don't know
other galaxies or
something and the current interface is
not really providing any good ways of of
specifying
that so what we would like to do is add
a new myth to the interface but that
breaks all the existing provider apps
because they I mean otherwise they will
all have to update their own code and go
in and add this method even though they
may not want to ship to other galaxies
or provide Dimension
calculations changing the method adding
another argument or so that also breaks
all the all the existing providers
actually changing anything on the
interface breaks existing
providers so another option would be we
could create a new interface and a new
enum that's possible but the existing
interface could be big we may even have
used it all sorts of places in our own
codebase that we will now have to create
a complete parallel code path to
ker4 and this could lead to a lot of
code duplication and the next time we
need to change
something in uh with regards to shipping
should we then create another parallel
implementation it doesn't really sound
appealing in any
way all we want is just to extend the
existing interface without changing or
breaking
everything
so what we have now introduced is a way
to extend interfaces this allows you to
create a new in interface that extend an
existing interface in this case I have
created the our express shipping
provider it allows vendors to uh add
calculations for express shipping let's
just say I'm inan a overnight shipping
or
something and they can add a new method
to the existing interface this is one of
the new features extending
interfaces syntax is you have the normal
interface declaration and then you add
extend and then a list of interfaces
that this interface
extends it also means that all
implementors of the new interface must
Implement all the methods from all the
interfaces both the interface itself and
all the interface it extends and
potential interfaces that those
extends so it will be a combined list of
all the methods from all the extended
interfaces how would this look as you
can see here this is the express
shipping provider it implements the
express shipping provider interface
which also implicitly means that it it
implements the I shipping provider I
haven't specified it on the implements
section here but it's implicit because I
express shipping provider implements I
shipping provider in this case I have to
implement all three methods get provider
name this case it's shipping Ros the
calculates shipping cost the one that
cames from the original interface
and now the new method here calculate
express shipping
costs for the enum here you can see I
actually only specifies the I shipping
provider as being implemented as the
express shipping provider and it still
works because express shipping provider
implicitly implements the ey shipping
provider so you can see it here
also it implements the original
interface
now we comes to the next feature which
is actually two in one because it's not
enough just to create a new interface
that would still be breaking but the
trick here is that we never changed the
enum the enum is still only providing
the I shipping provider
interface and that means that all the
extension out there implementing that
and adding a a value to the enum with
that interface will still work but then
is a trick how can we actually access
those that implements the new improved
interface and this is what we do down
here we have added a new uh way of
checking whether an interface implements
another interface this is the first line
if provider is express shipping
provider it's a it's a Boolean
expression that
tests if the provider also implements I
express shipping provider
and if it does that then we can cast it
using the S expression which is also new
so we can say if provider is I express
shipping provider the result of that
expression is now a iexpress shipping
provider and then we can call the
calculate express shipping cost on that
provider because now we have changed it
to be an iexpress shipping
provider and then we can add the results
to the costs
again so if you look at the syntax here
first the is operator that's the
checking part and in this case the
example takes an unknown interface which
is also something we added to the system
application um we have added a i an
unknown interface that you can use that
gives a common ground for anyone who
wants this kind of generic functionality
so I use this an example here so I can
test whether the interface here unknown
pass to this method is actually an
iextended shipping provider interface or
supports
it the left side must be an instance
either variable or parameter of type
interface or variant and yes you can
also use a variant here and it will look
inside the variant check if there's a
Code unit and check if that codee unit
actually
implements the interface type specified
on the right
side the S operator syntax is very much
alike but it the result value is instead
an um an interface of the type of the
right side and in case that the left
side cannot be cast to the right side
you will get an error
and this is why you should in most cases
check first whether the interface you
want to cast to is actually
implemented and now it's demo
time so let's try to see how it looks we
have the shipping cost calculator I can
enter distance and weight let me just
start by enter
distance 100 kilm and already here I get
some even though there is no weight on
it let's say it 5 kilos and as you can
see I actually get two cost calculations
from Shipping RS that's the one that
actually implements the new Express cost
and I can get both an eco-friendly
shipping by horses and super fast trains
planes and Automobiles and for the old
Grand Pass shipping doesn't support the
new express delivery so it will only
provide me with reliable and Cheap
shipping
the sample I have shown here is of
course a very simplified version of
reality you have all extensibility
requirements which are much more complex
than what I have shown here this is a
boil down version suitable for video but
you will probably have to do a lot more
work around this when you implement this
yourself but I think this is a very very
good addition to the existing interface
feature that will make it a lot more
useful thank you for watching and hope
you will use this to improve your own
extensibility thank you